Guide to the Ruth Asawa Papers M1585
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 2. Public Art Projects, 1964-2002; 2.
  - 2.5 Grand Hyatt Hotel, "San Francisco Fountain"
    - photographs
      - cleaning, 1996 (Box 206, Folder 5)
      - Rose Resnick Lighthouse for the Blind event, 1998 (Box 206, Folder 6)
      - slides (Box 207, Folder 1)
      - oversize (Flat-box 242, Folder 2)
    - Union Square Sculpture Cleanup [video], 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 45, Folder 4)
      Hyatt fountain cleaning, with Asawa present.
    - Fountain/Ruth. Elliot Davis. Fountain + Ruths [video], 1998-05; 1 videotape(s) (hi-8) (Box 46, Folder 10)
      Lighthouse for the Blind event at Hyatt fountain; [6:54] students and Aiko walk to 1116 Castro where Paul Lanier conducts a workshop making clay faces (with Ruth's assistance)
  - 2.6 Phoenix Civic Plaza, Arizona, 1971-1973
    Asawa designed a series of tied wire sculpture fountains for a Charles Luckman Associates project in Phoenix, Arizona. From the text of an enclosed banquet program marking their dedication: "These facile, airy forms appear to rest in water-filled urns where they are misted with a fine spray of water. The mist slowly trickles as shimmering droplets to the ends of the intricate branches and reluctantly returns to the fountain pools." The plaza has since been redesigned, and the disposition of Asawa’s art is unknown.
    - correspondence, memoranda, notes, printed items, etc. (Box 118, Folder 7)
    - photographs and slides (Box 207, Folder 2)
    - oversize blueprints, 1970-1973 (Map-folder 63)
  - 2.7 Japanese Tea Garden, Hagiwara plaque, 1970-2005
    Makoto Hagiwara was hired to run the Tea Garden in Golden Gate Park by John McClaren following the 1894 California Midwinter International Exposition, where the site served as a model "Japanese Village." The Hagiwara family were caretakers of the Japanese Tea Garden until World War Two, when they were forcibly relocated to Topaz. Their role in the development of the Japanese Tea Garden was not well known until the efforts of the John McClaren Society, Isabel Bachels, Raymond Clary, Ed Schuster and others. The plaques were sponsored by the Society, with some funding provided by George Hagiwara's donation of 740 tea pots from the original tea garden, which were then sold.
    The memorial was mounted on a carefully chosen and positioned rock. The plaque, which featured a statement honoring Makoto Hagiwara in English and Japanese as well as frogs, lizards, and flora, was cast at Berkeley Art Foundry.The plaque's dedication took place February 1974, during cherry blossom season. Sada Yamamoto, Makoto's adopted daughter, attended.
    This series contains correspondence and memoranda by Asawa, the San Francisco Recreation and Parks Commission, Art Commission, Supervisor Dianne Feinstein, George Hagiwara and others. There are also photographs, design sketches and notes. Besides the memorial plaques, there is also material about the Tea Garden's general history and concessions management, as well as the John McClaren Society's Sir Francis Scott Key statue restoration efforts.
    Other correspondence series also contain letters or notes by Schuster, Clary, George Hagiwara and other descendants. See also file for Asawa's 2000 plaque for master carpenter Shinshichi Nakatani. Asawa also illustrated Elizabeth McClintock's book about the Garden published by the McLaren Society in 1977.
    - correspondence, memoranda, notes, etc., 1970-2005 (Box 118, Folder 8)
    - articles, printed items, design sketches, photographs (Box 118, Folder 9)
    - photographs (Box 207, Folder 3)
    - California's Gold. Japanese Garden. #1712 [video], 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 46, Folder 9)
      "California's Gold" KCET Los Angeles/California Public Television program hosted by Huell Howser, touring Japanese Tea Garden in Golden Gate Park. Includes gardener, Hagiwara descendents. Plaque at 24:10
  - 2.8 Nihonmachi Pedestrian Mall, Japantown "Origami Fountains", 1972-2005
    In the early 1960s, the San Francisco Redevelopment Agency plan for Japantown called for a new design for Buchanan Mall, a pedestrian plaza on Buchanan Street between Post and Sutter, and architects Van Bourg, Nakamura, Katsura, Karney, Inc. subsequently partnered with Rai Okamoto and Okamoto Associates for the project.
    Okamoto, who had studied with Albers at Yale and saw Ruth Asawa's wire work in 1950s, first approached her in July 1973. The Board of Directors of the Nihonmachi Community Development Corporation, an umbrella organization for businesses, property owners, and the community, approved Asawa's involvement.
    This involvement was not just limited to the origami fountains, however; Ruth participated actively in the design of the entire mall, including benches with dough art side panels of Japanese fairy stories and a cobblestone path.
    Ruth attributed her fountain design to "Albers' design class where we worked with folded paper, and childhood experience with origami." She practiced with paper models and cast a small prototype before executing the full sculpture. Schrader Iron Works assembled and installed the fountains, which were made of corten steel.
    Opening ceremonies for the Nihonmachi Pedestrian Mall took place March 27, 1976. However, due to draught-related water rationing a year layer, the fountains were turned off. In 1979 the water was restored, but due to neglect and poor design the fountains did not functioning properly. Rust continued to be an issue. By 1992, Nihonmachi considered removing them. Asawa conceded they "never functioned as they were designed to," and allowed their removal in 1995. Some members of the community formed the Friends of the Origami Fountains in order to rally for their replacement.
    Subsequently, the Buchanan Street Mall Preservation and Renovation Organizational Group and its Ruth Asawa Fountains Task Force met throughout 1997, resulting in a Redevelopment Agency funded project that included recasting the fountains in bronze and an improved water pumping system. Working with Asawa were contractor John Handa and consulting engineer Watson Takahashi. Casting was done at Artworks Foundry in Berkeley with molds made from the original fountains. The rededication ceremony was held October 20, 1999. The origami fountains have been since been accepted in the S.F. Arts Commission's collection, thus ensuring their long term maintenance and care.
    - 1972-1999 (Box 119, Folder 1)
    - 1999-2005 (Box 119, Folder 2)
    - photographs (Box 207, Folder 4)
    - slides (Box 207, Folder 5)
    - snapshots (refabrication, installation, rededication) (Box 207, Folders 6-7)
    - oversize drawings and blueprints (Map-folder 64)
  - 2.9 Mission Viejo Center, 1977-1980
    In 1977, the Edward J. DeBartolo Corporation was developing the Mission Viejo Center shopping center in southern Orange County near San Juan Capistrano and wanted, as agent Tamara Thomas wrote to Asawa, "some kind of a sculpture or fountain sculpture for their project which would have a story-telling aspect to it along the lines of your San Francisco fountain." Ruth's design was accepted, and she and her team (Mieko, Aiko, Ken, Adam, Phyllis Matsuno, Mai Arbegast, and Janet Abramonitz) began their research and design phase by studying Californian and Native American history and nature. The eight bronze and eight concrete panels would form a series totaling nine feet high. Berkeley Art Foundry did the casting, and the sculpture was installed in the Fall of 1979. It is unknown (but unlikely) whether the sculpture is still present in the mall, now known as The Shops at Mission Viejo.
    - correspondence, memoranda, etc. (Box 119, Folder 3)
    - notes, sketches, blueprints, 1977-1980 (Box 119, Folder 4)
    - photographs and slides (Box 208, Folder 1)
    - oversize drawings, 1977-1978 (Flat-box 55, Folder 1)
  - 2.10 SF Department of Social Services, Children’s Play Area (cancelled), 1980 (Box 119, Folder 5)
  - 2.11 Las Vegas cast dough relief sculpture (proposal, cancelled), 1980 (Box 120, Folder 1)
  - 2.12 Merritt Hospital, Oakland, 1979-1981 (Box 120, Folder 2)
    Oakland architects Stone, Marraccini and Patterson worked with Dr. Bruce Anderson to feature art in various locations in Merrit Hospital. The files discuss the potential display of Asawa sculpture or a fountain, and in 1981 Helen Novy commissioned a wire sculpture for the hospital in memory of husband.
  - 2.13 University of California Berkeley Sather Tower bell, 1980-1981 (Box 120, Folder 3, Map-folder 75)
    In 1981, Asawa designed a bell for UC Berkeley’s Sather Tower, popularly known as The Campanile. She created a four-panel relief design featuring carvings of bears, seagulls, clipper ships, and other animals, which was then cast in France by Cirecast. Weighing over five tons, the "Great Bear Bell" faces the constellation Ursa Major and rings every hour.
  - 2.14 Ramada Renaissance / Parc 55 Hotel, "San Francisco Yesterday and Today", 1982-1987
    Asawa made a seven-panel frieze for the carriage entrance of a hotel at 55 Cyril Magnin Street (near Powell and Market Streets) with bas-relief images of San Francisco area people and places, similiar to Hyatt fountain on the other side of Union Square. Daniel, Mann, Johnson and Mendenhall were architects for the then-U.S. Hotelier Associates property, and Asawa was contracted through a broker for the project.
    Since brass would be too heavy for the scale of the panels, Asawa used glass-fiber reinforced concrete, her first experience with the material. The reliefs originated in carved styrofoam, which was then coated with a layer of bakers clay (using 700 pounds of flour) and sealed with wax. After having a series of molds created, the concrete panels were produced by Lafayette Manufacturing in Hayward.
    Design planning for the frieze began with copious research at the Bancroft Library, San Francisco Maritime Museum, the California Academy of Sciences and elsewhere. There are many sketches, photocopies, and photographs here, some of which may have been recycled from the Hyatt project. Albert Lanier, Cyril Magnin, cable car gripman Fay Royal Baxter, and many others are represented on the panels.
    Architect Bud Duffy did the renderings. Paul Lanier and a friend built the plywood base from Albert's design. The workshop team also included Mae Lee, Mary Lee, Naoe Fukuyama and Laurie Lanier, as well as apprentices Robert Rajiewski (Academy of Art) and SOTA students Tamie Passalalpi and Erwin Lerias. Full credits are on the frieze itself. "San Francisco Yesterday and Today" was unveiled October 4, 1984. Tickets were sold as a benefit for the School Of the Arts. The hotel is now known as the Parc 55, owned by Wyndham Hotels.
    - correspondence, memoranda, notes, etc. (Box 120, Folder 4)
    - articles, printed items, sketches (Box 120, Folder 5)
    - research files (Box 80, Folders 1-9)
    - photographs, slides, contact sheets (Box 208, Folders 3-8)
    - oversize drawings, blueprints, architectural renderings, etc., 1984 (Map-folder 62)
  - 2.15 Father Boeddeker Park, "Redding School, Self-Portrait", 1983-1987
    Landscape architects Royston, Hanamoto, Alley and Abbey worked with the Recreation and Parks Department in developing a park and receation center at the corner of Jones, Eddy, and Ellis Streets, a site once home to a bowling alley, pinball arcade and grocery store. Asawa created a frieze wall in the Tiny Tot area, with her now-familiar dough figures cast in glass-reinforced concrete. The dough was molded with children from Redding Elementary School and other local residents, resulting in a 4'x16' concrete mural, cast once again using Lafayette Manufacturing. In March of 1983, the park opened under the provisional name of Saint Francis Park, but a year later it was officially named honoring Father Alfred Boeddeker. The Asawa frieze was conserved and re-installed while park underwent a complete overhaul in the Fall of 2014.
    - correspondence, notes, etc. (Box 120, Folder 6)
    - photographs (Box 208, Folder 2)
    - oversize blueprints (Map-folder 67)
  - 2.16 Public Memorial to Congressman Phillip Burton (proposal), 1984 (Box 120, Folder 7)
  - 2.17 Bayside Plaza, "Aurora Fountain", 1984-1986
    For her fifth fountain in San Francisco, Asawa returned to the origami form. The Aurora Fountain, located at 188 Embarcadero at Howard Street, features 120 triangles of polished stainless steel fit together in a 13 foot circle. Bayside Plaza was an Embarcadero South Investors development with Ed Tower as architect. Albert Lanier and Lanier/Sherrill/Morrison did some calculations and design work, and fabrication was done by Robert Yick and Latter Manufacturing Company (which usually constructed plant equipment). Landscape architect Mai Arbegast designed the 22 foot-diameter pool and contributed to the overall plaza design. Gaps in the fountain's progress were due to Ruth's bout with lupus and the removal of the Embarcadero Freeway. Opening ceremonies took place March 19, 1986, with Mayor Dianne Feinstein turning on the water and a coin toss benefiting Alvarado.
    - correspondence, memoranda, notes, etc. (Box 121, Folder 1)
    - photographs (Box 209, Folder 1)
    - slides (Box 209, Folder 2)
    - snapshots (Box 209, Folder 3)
    - oversize blueprints, patterns, architectural drawings, 1986 (Map-folder 71)
    - Tower Architects/Mai Arbegast oversize material, 1985-1986 (Map-folder 71)
    - oversize photographs (Flat-box 242, Folder 1)
  - 2.18 Santa Rosa Courthouse Square fountain, 1984-1993
    In the early 1980s, Santa Rosa's Old Courthouse Square was renovated as part of Redevelopment Agency downtown revitalization efforts. A Fine Arts Committee first began looking for artists in 1979. Prior to Asawa's involvement, local artist Bruce Johnson had been selected, but the City Council overruled the jury, rejecting his winning entry. He later sued the city and won.
    Asawa began as a consultant in 1984 amidst the controversy, but was eventually selected to create one of her dough relief murals for a fountain in the square. Legal discussions and prolonged contract negotiation occurred amidst media scrutiny, including the publishing of her $100,000 fee. Many (including a group called "Artists in the Schools of Sonoma County" and Johnson himself) urged her to withdraw. A few even protested at the fountain’s opening.
    However, Asawa continued to receive support from people such as Steve Burke, Director of Housing and Redevelopment, and Mayor Donna Born, who hosted history meetings at her home, referred her to historians, and contributed to the mural. Other community representatives also came to the workshop and sculpted dough.
    Work on the mural offically began in January 1986. Surrounding the 32 foot-long fountain would be four panels of Sonoma County history and nature, including images of Luther Burbank's farm, Jack London's Wolf House, and marine wildlife molded by over 300 students from nearby Burbank Elementary School. Asawa also employed a staff of ten, including Nancy Thompson, Atsuko Sells, Aiko Cuneo and Paul Lanier. The panels were cast in glass reinforced concrete by Lafayette.
    Following a logistically complex installation, the fountain was dedicated February 7, 1987. Beginning in 2016, the square underwent a significant re-design, and the mural panels were placed in storage until funds can be raised for their installation on the south side of the square.
    - 1984 (Box 121, Folder 2)
    - 1985 (Box 121, Folder 3)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 121, Folder 4)
    - articles, printed items, childrens' letters and artwork, etc. (Box 121, Folder 5)
    - research files (Box 81, Folder 1-6)
    - photographs (Box 209, Folders 4-5)
    - slides (Box 209, Folder 6)
    - oversize concept and scale drawings, blue and sepia prints, architectural renderings, etc., 1986-1987 (Map-folder 61)
    - Ruth Asawa and Steve From Santa Rosa Project Feb. 26?; March 7, 1985. Sandy Nozenzo on "Calvin Brown/Anna Harmon." John Hoode / Sandy Nozenzo, John Hood [audio], 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 41, Folder 6)
      Side A: telephone conversation between Ruth Asawa and Steve Burke, City of Santa Rosa re: Bruce Johnson, diagnosis, extension on project 1985-02-26; [13:58] Ruth Asawa interviewing Sandy Nozenzo about family history 1985-03-07 (Santa Rosa); [25:46] answering machine message re: acupuncture; [28:57] Ruth Asawa outgoing answering machine message re: bronze casting. Side B: meeting re: Santa Rosa.
    - TV 50 Show - Ruth Asawa [video], 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 43, Folder 1)
      "Ruth Asawa: Courting History" TV news segment re: Santa Rosa fountain.
    - Old Courthouse Square Fountain [slideshow], 2010-01-19; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd) (Box 79, Folder 8)
      Slideshow set to music with photographs of Santa Rosa commission.
  - 2.19 Beringer Winery, St. Helena "History of Wine" fountain, 1987-1988
    In recognition of the 150th anniversary of viniculture in Napa Valley and the 112th birthday of the Beringer brand, Wine World, Inc. (then owner of Beringer) hired Asawa to create a signature fountain for the Beringer Winery at 2000 Main St. St. Helena, California. The center of the fountain features a large bronze amphora eight feet high and three feet in diameter, with a relief pattern made of baker's clay.
    This historical mural included George Yount, the first Napan to plant grapevines in 1838, and Jacob and Frederick Beringer, the German immigrants and winemakers who established the winery in 1876. Nancy Thompson did research and all the drawings. Paul Lanier, Addie Lanier, and Mae Lee also assisted. The sculpture was cast by Artworks Foundry, and dedicated November 16, 1988. It stands in the courtyard behind the Rhine House on the property.
    - correspondence, notes, etc. (Box 121, Folder 6)
    - printed items, photographs, clippings, sketches, work journal, research material (Box 81, Folder 7)
    - photographs (Box 210, Folder 1)
    - slides (Box 210, Folder 2)
    - snapshots (Box 210, Folder 3)
    - oversize drawings, blue and sepia prints, etc. (Flat-box 55, Folder 13, Tube 70, Map-folder 69)
    - Bay Area Backroads KRON-TV [video], 1990-04-01; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 45, Folder 11)
      Beringer Winery profile. 4:56 "Ruth's Cast Piece at Beringer is Shown Very Briefly"
  - 2.20 Murphy Street Public Art Project, Sunnyvale (not completed), 1988-1989
    - correspondence, notes, etc., 1988-1989 (Box 122, Folder 1)
    - Nancy Thompson drawing proposal, 1988-11-02 (Map-folder 76)
  - 2.21 Allright Auto Park, Little Tokyo, Los Angeles (proposal), 1988 (Box 122, Folder 2, Map-folder 60)
  - 2.22 San Jose Japanese-American Internment Memorial, 1985-1994
    In many ways this sculpture was the culmination of Ruth's public installation career. It certainly is the best documented. In July 1989, the Commission on the Internment of Local Japanese Americans, in conjunction with the City of San Jose, the City Council, Transit Mall Art Committee, and the Fine Arts Commission selected Asawa to create an internment memorial. The Commission also mandated an oral history project, a curriculum guide, and the construction of a resource center.
    The six foot-high and 14 foot-long bronze monument stands at 280 South First Street near the Robert F. Peckham Federal Building. Peckham had assisted with returning property to former internees after the war. Due to administrative delays, contract negotiation, and the Loma Prieta earthquake, the project was slow to begin. A great deal of correspondence concerns insurance, legal matters, and installation logistics. Among the correspondents are Richard Tanaka, chair of the Internment Commission, Mayor Ron Gonzales, Representative Norm Mineta, Jerry Hiura of the Fine Arts Commission, and David Allen, acting director of the Office of Cultural Affairs.
    Research, drafting, and dough sculpting was done with Nancy Thompson, Paul Lanier, and Addie Lanier. East Bay sculptor Dennis Fujimoto also helped. Nancy's work journal provides excellent insight to the project's daily progress.
    The memorial's two long sides depict prewar nikkei scenes on one side and images representing internment, the 442nd Infantry Regiment and other JA soldiers, and the redress movement on the other. Historical accuracy was an important design component, and the research phase was extensive. The team talked to hundreds of people at senior centers and historical societies and sought community leader feedback on images once the design was drafted. Ruth was quoted in a 1997 SJSU magazine article: "I used my house and our farm and sheds. I represented orchards and vegetable farms in the Santa Clara Valley. I tried to represent the Buddhist temple and other actual buildings in San Jose where Japanese-Americans congregated. All of us had the same experience."
    Each end of the sculpture features family crests known as mon, which were solicited from as many local residents as could be found. Ads were placed in several newspapers. In the end, 177 mon were used, including those of Representatives Norman Mineta and Robert Matsui, resistors Fred Korematsu, Gordon Hirabayashi, and Minoru Yasui, and 442nd veteran Wayne Kanemoto. Ruth's friends also contributed their mon, including Kiku Funabiki, Ibuki Hibi Lee, Mai Kitazawa Arbegast, Janice Mirikitani, Kay Sekimachi, Alice Takemoto, and June Watanabe. Ruth's sister Mary Oye sent in the Asawa crest. The mon correspondence files contain many remembrances and other details. Refer to the Internment series for related material.
    Artworks Foundry cast the bronze, and Lafayette manufactured a concrete base. The memorial was installed in February 1994, and dedicated in March with a taiko performance and speakers including Norm Mineta and Fred Korematsu, who remarked "I have heard people say that they didn't know anything about the internment. Well, here it is... And for those who don't want to talk about it, well, this will talk for them."
    - working file 1, 1985-1991 (Box 122, Folder 3)
    - working file 2, 1991-1994 (Box 122, Folder 4)
    - design, project notes, photographs (Box 122, Folder 5)
    - text, key to panels (Box 122, Folder 6)
    - internment stories, correspondence (Box 123, Folder 1)
    - miscellaneous correspondence re: mons (Box 123, Folder 2)
    - mon A-I correspondence (Box 123, Folder 3)
    - mon J-N correspondence (Box 123, Folder 4)
    - mon O-Z correspondence (Box 124, Folder 1)
    - mon index cards (unfoldered) (Box 178)
    - work journals (Box 124, Folder 2)
    - dedication (Box 124, Folder 3)
    - publicity (Box 124, Folder 4)
    - research files (Box 82, Folders 1-9, Box 83, Folders 1-13)
    - photographs
      - prints (Box 210, Folder 4)
      - slides (Box 210, Folder 5)
      - snapshots (Box 211, Folders 1-3, Box 210, Folder 6)
      - two photo albums [unfoldered] (Box 212)
      - drymounted prints by Terry Schmitt [unfoldered] (Flat-box 239, Flat-box 240)
      - oversize (Flat-box 241, Folder 10)
    - A/V
      - Ruth Asawa. San Jose Internment. Artworks Foundry, Terry Schmitt, 1994; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 46, Folder 1)
        Unedited footage shot by Terry Schmitt. The San Jose Japanese American Internment Memorial was constructed in a studio adjoining the Mussi Artworks Foundry in Berkeley. First eight minutes shows operations at foundry, rest is Nancy Thompson, Paul Lanier, and Ruth Asawa working with baker's clay.
      - San Jose Internment Memorial, 1994-01-27; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 46, Folder 2)
        San Jose Museum of Art program previewing March 1994 unveiling. Program produced by Educational Curator Madelyn Crawford. Introduced by Jerry Hiura. Asawa slide presentation begins 13:40.